[
  {
    "question": "Which PRIMARY thematic question does The Lathe of Heaven explore through Orr’s special ability?",
    "a": "What are the most pressing problems in modern-day society?",
    "b": "How can we solve the problem of overpopulation?",
    "c": "How can we know what is truly real?",
    "d": "Why is it important to have dreams?",
    "e": "How does technology affect our perception of reality?",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Lathe of Heaven was published amidst a background of sociopolitical conflict over the",
    "a": "Civil Rights Movement",
    "b": "Cuban Missile Crisis",
    "c": "Iran-Contra Affair",
    "d": "Vietnam War",
    "e": "Stonewall riots",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which president was responsible for the Watergate scandal?",
    "a": "Johnson",
    "b": "Nixon",
    "c": "Reagan",
    "d": "Bush",
    "e": "Clinton",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do Haber and Lelache both respond to Orr’s ability to alter reality?",
    "a": "They want to help him better understand his ability.",
    "b": "They want to use his ability for their own personal gain.",
    "c": "They find his ability unbelievable even after they witness it.",
    "d": "They want to use his ability for purely altruistic purposes.",
    "e": "They feel jealous that they do not have the same ability.",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does Orr work at the beginning of the novel?",
    "a": "the Fire Department",
    "b": "the Parks Department",
    "c": "the Housing Department",
    "d": "the Public Works Department",
    "e": "the Health Department",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does Le Guin FIRST introduce Taoist philosophy to The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "through the books Orr reads",
    "b": "through the excerpts included in the preface",
    "c": "through the quotes engraved in Haber’s HURAD office",
    "d": "through the epigraphs that begin each chapter",
    "e": "through Orr and Haber’s philosophical discussions",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Taoist philosophy emphasizes the search for",
    "a": "chastity and holiness",
    "b": "equality and justice",
    "c": "empathy and selflessness",
    "d": "rationality and order",
    "e": "equilibrium and balance",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote Utopia?",
    "a": "Victor Hugo",
    "b": "Thomas More",
    "c": "Mary Shelley",
    "d": "Aphra Behn",
    "e": "John Milton",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does Haber exemplify Western philosophical viewpoints?",
    "a": "He acts selflessly and always places others before himself.",
    "b": "He has no problem with using others for his own personal gain.",
    "c": "He strives to be the best possible version of himself.",
    "d": "He prioritizes the search for inner peace.",
    "e": "He believes in logic and rational thought.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which character’s beliefs MOST strongly reflect Taoist and Buddhist philosophies?",
    "a": "E’nememen Asfah",
    "b": "Heather Lelache",
    "c": "Tiua’k Ennbe Ennbe",
    "d": "George Orr",
    "e": "Mannie Ahrens",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the beginning of the novel, Orr is dying from",
    "a": "a workplace injury",
    "b": "alcohol poisoning",
    "c": "radiation sickness",
    "d": "tuberculosis",
    "e": "battle wounds",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Chapter Three, Orr sees headlines announcing conflict between the United States and",
    "a": "Turkey",
    "b": "China",
    "c": "Afghanistan",
    "d": "Cuba",
    "e": "Japan",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do Haber and Orr solve the issue of overpopulation?",
    "a": "by reducing the population through a series of pandemics",
    "b": "by having humanity colonize other planets so we can have access to more resources",
    "c": "by creating a new labor system that produces enough food for everyone on Earth",
    "d": "by fostering cooperation between world leaders to improve the global distribution of resources",
    "e": "by using nuclear warfare to drastically reduce the population",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does Orr create a reality with aliens when Haber prompts him to dream of peace?",
    "a": "They can take the place of humanity’s previous world leaders and lead more rationally.",
    "b": "They can destroy the weapons used to fuel wars.",
    "c": "They can provide humanity with enough resources to make war unnecessary.",
    "d": "They provide a common enemy against which humanity can unite.",
    "e": "They can teach humanity about the futility of war.",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Orr subconsciously views the concept of war as",
    "a": "futile and meaningless",
    "b": "a tragic yet necessary means to an end",
    "c": "irrational yet inescapable",
    "d": "abhorrent and inexcusable",
    "e": "a powerful but dangerous political tool",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Heather Lelache’s parents first meet in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "a court hearing",
    "b": "an amusement park",
    "c": "a political demonstration",
    "d": "an airport",
    "e": "a concert hall",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happened to Heather Lelache’s mother at age thirty-eight in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "She was expelled from law school.",
    "b": "She died after using a dirty needle for heroin.",
    "c": "She was mugged after moving to Portland, Oregon.",
    "d": "She became ill after moving to Ghana.",
    "e": "She got injured at work.",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What concept does Heather Lelache struggle with because of her perceptions of her parents’ feelings towards each other in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "marriage",
    "b": "the passage of time",
    "c": "her racial identity",
    "d": "selflessness",
    "e": "the gender pay gap",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Critics have MOST often noted that Le Guin's depiction of Heather LeLache",
    "a": "essentializes her race",
    "b": "trivializes her feelings for George Orr",
    "c": "was unnecessary to further the plot",
    "d": "depicts an atypical woman’s perspective",
    "e": "does not explore her family background",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which issue does Dr. Haber mention after George Orr dreams of a world without racial conflict?",
    "a": "colorism in Japan",
    "b": "segregation in the United States",
    "c": "the caste system of India",
    "d": "antisemitism in Germany",
    "e": "Sámi assimilation in Norway",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens right after George Orr dreams about eliminating all race-based suffering in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "Biodiversity falls dramatically.",
    "b": "Global war erupts.",
    "c": "The Earth moves very close to the Sun.",
    "d": "Three-quarters of the Earth’s population disappears.",
    "e": "Everyone turns gray.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following concepts is NOT related to how the aliens integrated into society in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "gender equality",
    "b": "immigration",
    "c": "migration",
    "d": "race and racism",
    "e": "xenophobia",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which animal did the aliens’ suits resemble in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "dinosaurs",
    "b": "turtles",
    "c": "lizards",
    "d": "frogs",
    "e": "snakes",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who helps George Orr recover from a toxic mixture of drugs after a nuclear war in the beginning of The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "Heather Lelache’s father",
    "b": "Mannie Ahrens (his apartment manager) and a medic",
    "c": "Heather Lelache",
    "d": "Dr. William Haber",
    "e": "E’nememen Asfa",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What causes Dr. William Haber to eventually lose his sanity in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "near-daily exposure to aliens",
    "b": "his desire to not develop powers similar to those of George Orr",
    "c": "his inability to empathize with anyone",
    "d": "his jealousy of Heather Lelache’s career success",
    "e": "sleep deprivation",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do Dr. William Haber’s attitudes towards others differ from those of George Orr in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "He prefers solitude.",
    "b": "He prefers close connections.",
    "c": "He feels inferior to them.",
    "d": "He accepts help more easily.",
    "e": "He speaks highly of them.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What detail does Dr. Haber continually forget about George Orr in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "his sleep patterns",
    "b": "his name",
    "c": "his reasons for seeking treatment",
    "d": "his treatment plan",
    "e": "his work schedule",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What organization comes to Heather Lelache’s mind when she first meets George Orr in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "Student NonviolentCoordinating Committee (SNCC)",
    "b": "Third World Women’s Alliance (TWWA)",
    "c": "Lowndes County Freedom Organization (LCFO)",
    "d": "Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC)",
    "e": "Workers World Party (WWP)",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "After Heather Lelache hypnotically suggests that George Orr dream that aliens are no longer on the moon in The Lathe of Heaven, the aliens",
    "a": "appear on Uranus",
    "b": "fly to Saturn",
    "c": "are transformed into humans",
    "d": "disappear from existence",
    "e": "invade the earth",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What patterns are presented as incorrect in The Lathe of Heaven?",
    "a": "dominance and control",
    "b": "rigidity and dedication",
    "c": "passivity and ennui",
    "d": "friendship and love",
    "e": "openness and understanding",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  }
]

